The Victor D'Amico Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series IV. Children's Art Carnival and Caravan, 1940s-1979 (bulk 1942-1965)
  - Subseries IV.C. Children's Art Caravan, 1960s-1974
    - Prospectus for a project to develop a mobile program of art education for elementary school pupils, April 1968; Proposed for five Georgia counties, submitted to John D. Rockefeller, 3rd, Foundation. (Box 24, Folder IV.C.5)
    - Plans and models, 1968; Color and b/w photographic prints (some mounted), color transparencies (Box 24, Folder IV.C.6)
    - General information, 1968-1970; Includes proposal, b/w and color photographs of Caravan model, clipping of D'Amico article "The Children's Art Caravan" (Arts and Activities, October 1970) (Box 24, Folder IV.C.7)
    - Boston Artmobile, October 1969; Color slides (Box 24, Folder IV.C.8)
    - Correspondence and reports, 1969-1972; Includes emended draft and final versions of "Promoting the Children's Art Caravan: A Report" (10/15/1970), prepared for Institute of Modern Art’s Board of Trustees (Box 24, Folder IV.C.9)
    - General information, 1969-1972; Includes clippings, information on trailers, list of attendees at 9/26/1972 conference on Art Caravan (see folder IV.C.18) (Box 24, Folder IV.C.10)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1974; Includes clippings, fundraising, letters of support for the project from Henry Allen Moe, Clark Foundation (and MoMA Trustee); and John Hightower, NY State Council on the Arts (later MoMA Director), among others (Box 24, Folder IV.C.11)
    - Model of Caravan, July 1970; From original envelope labeled "Photos Carnivals & Caravan - model and article": b/w prints (Box 24, Folder IV.C.12)
    - Trailer for possible use as Caravan, 1970, 1972; Floor plans and specifications, proposed budgets (Box 24, Folder IV.C.13)
    - Proposed budgets, 1970, 1973; Includes some correspondence to potential funders (Box 24, Folder IV.C.14)
    - National Endowment for the Arts, 1970-1972; Correspondence (Box 24, Folder IV.C.15)
    - Grant application, July 1971; To the National Endowment for the Arts (Box 24, Folder IV.C.16)
    - Specifications for trailers, December 1972; From Avid Corporation; includes correspondence, explanation of specifications, whiteprints (Box 24, Folder IV.C.17)
    - Conference on the Art Caravan, 1972; Includes statements from Board of Education and other participants, sketches and plans, description of planned Caravan (Box 24, Folder IV.C.18)
- Series V. Art Barge, 1950s-2011 (bulk 1955-1980s)
  The subseries includes some administrative records (registration forms, expenses) and extensive photographic documentation of summer art programs, including students at work, exhibitions, and social events, held at the Art Barge during and after D'Amico's tenure at MoMA.
  MoMA began summer painting classes for adults on eastern Long Island in 1955, at Ashawaugh Hall, East Hampton, near the summer home of Victor and Mabel D'Amico. The Institute of Modern Art, formed at MoMA in 1960, ran summer programs starting in 1962 on the decommissioned U.S. Navy coal barge Kearsarge, which had been towed from New Jersey to Napeague Harbor in Amagansett, Long Island. This location came to be called The Art Barge. In the off-seasons, D'Amico gathered interested adult students, into groups variously named Kearsarge or Napeague, in New York City for criticism and art review.
  In 1971, The Napeague Institute of Art was founded as an independent organization under charter from the State of New York Board of Regents, with its own board of trustees and officers, dedicated to "the creative development of laymen, students, teachers, and professional artists, helping them to achieve a richer way of life and make a more meaningful contribution to society." It ran summer programs at the Art Barge (which it leased from MoMA until October 1982) for senior citizens, school teachers, adults, and children. Some teacher education classes there were offered for credit through New York University (1963-1966) and Southampton College of Long Island University (beginning in 1967). In 1982, The Napeague Institute of Art was renamed the Victor D'Amico Institute of Art. It continues to administer summer programs at The Art Barge under that name.
  Many of the color slides in this series were originally housed unsorted in large boxes, unidentified as to content or date. They are now organized generally into groupings by apparent subject and year printed on the slide housing; researchers should note that these designations are approximate. Images of unidentified art works have been transferred to the Department of Education for internal use. Meeting minutes have been removed per the Museum Archives' Access Policy.
  - D'Amico Amagansett, Undated; Two Super 8 film reels; NOTE: These Super 8 film reels have been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center, which has the proper facilities for storing and screening them. Researchers should contact the Study Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the films’ physical condition. (Box 25, Folder V.1)
  - “Victor D’Amico Museum of Modern Art”, Undated; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 25, Folder V.2)
  - Notes in D'Amico’s hand, Undated (Box 25, Folder V.3)
  - Postcard reproduction of ship card for Kearsarge, Undated (Box 25, Folder V.4)
  - Students at work, finished works, 1950s; B/w prints and negatives, color prints (Box 25, Folder V.5)
  - Exterior views, with students working, [1950s]; B/w prints, mounted (Box 71, Folder V.6*)
  - Summer Vacation Painting Classes (1 of 3), 1955; Acceptances for program’s first year (Box 25, Folder V.7)
  - Summer Vacation Painting Classes (2 of 3), 1955-1960; Questionnaires re: summer painting classes, and responses. Includes completed forms and some personalized letters (Box 25, Folder V.8)
  - Summer Vacation Painting Classes (3 of 3), 1956; Questionnaires re: summer painting classes sent to participants to determine interest for planned second year of classes (Box 25, Folder V.9)
  - Completed enrollment forms (1 of 3), 1955, 1956 (Box 25, Folder V.10)
  - Completed enrollment forms (2 of 3), 1957, 1958 (Box 25, Folder V.11)
  - Completed enrollment forms (3 of 3), 1959, 1960 (Box 26, Folder V.12)
  - MoMA interoffice memos, 1955-1961; Re: administrative matters including tuition payments and petty cash (Box 26, Folder V.13)
  - Student field trip to Lazy Point; Gratitude Day, 1955, 1979; Color slides (Box 26, Folder V.14)
  - Ashawagh Hall, East Hampton (Long Island, NY), circa 1956; Photographs of first location of MoMA summer classes: color slides (Box 26, Folder V.15)
  - Summer Vacation Painting Class #1, July 18, 1958; 7" audio reel. Contents listed on box: roundtable discussion, summer classes Ashawagh Hall, Charlotte Park, Ralph Carpentier, Jack Ramsay, Mabel D'Amico, Ione Ulrich, Joe Lane, D'Amico.; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 26, Folder V.16)
  - Summer Vacation Painting Class #2, [July 18, 1958]; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 26, Folder V.17)
  - Children's art classes, East Hampton, Summer 1958; B/w prints (Box 26, Folder V.18)
  - Indoor and outdoor views, students at work, Art Barge and Art Caravan models, 1958-1962, undated; B/w prints (Box 26, Folder V.19)
  - Self-criticism, January 1959; By Hilde Sigal: original manuscript and typed transcript (Box 26, Folder V.20)
  - Interior and exterior views, students at work, 1959, [1960s]; B/w prints (Box 26, Folder V.21)
  - “Xmas Motivation # 6”, [1959]; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 26, Folder V.22)
  - “Xmas (Original Good)”, 1959; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 26, Folder V.23)
  - Students at work: exterior views, 1960s; Color and b/w transparencies (Box 26, Folder V.24)
  - Students at work indoors; exterior views, [1960s]; Mounted b/w snapshots (Box 26, Folder V.25)
  - Interior and exterior views; students at work indoors and outdoors, [1960s]; B/w and color prints, b/w negatives, color stereo transparencies (Box 26, Folder V.26)
  - Exhibitions, students at work indoors and outdoors, [1960s]; Photos by Jay Hoops: b/w prints (Box 26, Folder V.27)
  - Creative Art Education Workshops, [1960s]; Metal stamp with summer schedule at Art Barge (Box 27, Folder V.28)
  - “Class criticism summer”, [1960s]; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 27, Folder V.29)
  - “Drawing leaves etc. new 2 sides”, [1960s]; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 27, Folder V.30)
  - Kearsarge Group: First motivation drawings, [1960s]; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 27, Folder V.31)
  - Correspondence, promotional material, group mailings, application for state charter, D'Amico resumés, 1960s-1970s; Includes note D'Amico-members (9/19/1973) outlining history of Institute of Modern Art, Kearsarge Group, and Napeague Institute of Art (Box 27, Folder V.32)
  - Audiomotivator, [1960s]; 7" audio reel; D'Amico handwritten list of music excerpts included on tape.; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 27, Folder V.33)
  - Directions on cameras with [illegible], [1960s]; 7" audio reel; NOTE: In Spring, 2013, this recording was sent off-site for preservation. The preservation vendor concluded that the tape was blank. (Box 27, Folder V.34)
  - First meeting Art Barge teachers, [1960s]; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 27, Folder V.35)
  - Teachers interview, [1960s]; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 28, Folder V.36)
  - Designs and plans, [1960s]; Including D'Amico residence in Mt. Vernon, NY, and “Mabel’s beach house”: original tracings and whiteprints (Box 73, Folder V.37*)
  - Students at work, D'Amico in classes, [1960s-1970s]; B/w photographs (Box 28, Folder V.38)
  - List of books donated to East Hampton Free Library by Napeague Institute of Art, [1960s-1970s] (Box 28, Folder V.39)
  - Buchman party, summer 1960, 7” audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 28, Folder V.40)
  - Barge bill of sale, building permit, March 28, November 24, 1961 (Box 28, Folder V.41)
  - Applications and class lists, 1961 (Box 28, Folder V.42)
  - Fundraising letters sent to class participants, 1961; Carbon copies (Box 28, Folder V.43)
  - Various individuals, art works, 1961, undated; Color and b/w prints; b/w negative (Box 28, Folder V.44)
  - Art Barge model, 1961; B/w prints, one mounted and marked for layout (Box 28, Folder V.45)
  - Art Barge in situ, under construction, 1961, undated; B/w prints, one mounted for reproduction; b/w negatives (Box 28, Folder V.46)
  - Exteriors, Art Barge being towed, events at Art Barge, 1961-1966, undated; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 28, Folder V.47)
  - Students working in class, indoors and outdoors, 1961-1967; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 28, Folder V.48)
  - Students working in class, indoors and out, 1961-1968; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 28, Folder V.49)
  - Exterior views, indoor and outdoor classes, D'Amico, 1961-1969, 1987, 1990; Color slides (Box 28, Folder V.50)
  - Clippings, 1961, 1982, undated; From The New York Times and other newspapers (Box 28, Folder V.51)
  - Finished works; D'Amico outdoors by bridge; interiors of Art Barge, 1962; Color slides (Box 28, Folder V.52)
  - Airplane visit to Art Barge; Saturday critique, 1962, 1964; Color slides (Box 28, Folder V.53)
  - Construction and interior views, students at work, 1962-1968; Color slides (Box 28, Folder V.54)
  - Students at work indoors and outdoors, 1962-1968; Color slides (Box 28, Folder V.55)
  - Finished works, students at work, 1962-1969; From an unlabeled box: color paper-mounted and b/w glass-mounted slides (Box 28, Folder V.56)
  - Exhibitions of student work, 1962-1969; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 28, Folder V.57)
  - Students working, indoors and outdoors; exterior views, 1962-1970; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 28, Folder V.58)
  - Parties, students relaxing indoors and outdoors, 1962-1970; Color slides (Box 28, Folder V.59)
  - Views of the Barge site, students, art work, 1962-1971; Color slides (Box 28, Folder V.60)
  - Students at work indoors and outdoors, 1962-1973; Color slides (Box 28, Folder V.61)
  - Clippings, correspondence, D'Amico obituary notices, 1962-2001; Materials from former MoMA art teacher Arlette Buchman originally collected in a folder marked "Victor's work." Includes agreement with MoMA (11/28/1973) re: rental of land and building for Art Barge (Box 29, Folder V.62)
  - Cancelled applications for summer classes, 1963; Forms, carbon correspondence (Box 29, Folder V.63)
  - Students at work indoors and outdoors; interior views, 1963, undated; B/w prints on album pages previously removed (Box 29, Folder V.64)
  - Charles Francis Cook lounge: interior views, [1963, undated]; Enlarged views of some images in folder V.64: b/w mounted prints, with adhesive for hanging (Box 29, Folder V.65)
  - Students at work indoors and outdoors, 1963-1969; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 29, Folder V.66)
  - Students at work indoors and outdoors, 1963-1969; Color slides (Box 29, Folder V.67)
  - Teachers' classes, two students at work, 1963-1970; Color slides (Box 29, Folder V.68)
  - Students at work, finished work, 1963-1970; Color slides (Box 29, Folder V.69)
  - Interior and exterior views, students at work, 1963-1976; Color slides (Box 29, Folder V.70)
  - Action painting class: students at work outdoors, 1964; Color slides (Box 29, Folder V.71)
  - Students working on outdoor mural, 1964, 1965, 1967-1969; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 29, Folder V.72)
  - Summer classes, 1964, 1967; Contact sheets, b/w and color negatives (Box 29, Folder V.73)
  - Students at work, finished works, 1964-1969; Color slides (Box 29, Folder V.74)
  - Teachers' workshops, 1964-1969; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 29, Folder V.75)
  - Teachers’ mural: students at work, 1965; Color slides (Box 29, Folder V.76)
  - Group labeled "Barge portraits": individual students with their work, 1965, 1967; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 29, Folder V.77)
  - Summer art programs, 1965, 1972-1982; Workshops for teachers: recommendations, reports to funders, notices, clipping (Box 29, Folder V.78)
  - D'Amico motivations, 1965, undated; Poems, ideas, sketches (Box 29, Folder V.79)
  - Motivations, 1965-1968; Photographs of visual stimuli to creativity; exterior views: color slides (Box 30, Folder V.80)
  - Motivations, 1965-1968; Written stimuli to creativity, for painting classes; some in D'Amico’s hand (Box 30, Folder V.81)
  - Motivations, [1965-1968]; Written stimuli to creativity: poems and themes (Box 30, Folder V.82)
  - Motivations, [1965-1968]; Written stimuli to creativity (Box 30, Folder V.83)
  - Project descriptions and motivations for painting classes, [1965-1968] (Box 30, Folder V.84)
  - Art appreciation, teachers, 1967; 7" audio reel, unboxed; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 30, Folder V.85)
  - Mural, students working, art works, 1967-1968; Color slides (Box 30, Folder V.86)
  - Murals, July 1967; July 1969; Photographs of students working on mural; finished piece: color slides (Box 30, Folder V.87)
  - Students at work; interior and exterior views, 1967-1970; Color slides (Box 30, Folder V.88)
  - Clippings, 1967-2002; Some are about MoMA in general (Box 30, Folder V.89)
  - Plans for rope fence, benches, other designs, May 1968; undated; Original drawings and tracings, whiteprints; oversize, see flat file 2-2 (Box flat file 2-2, Folder V.90*)
  - August teachers' workshop; teachers leaving Art Barge, Summer 1968; Three Super 8 film reels; Note: These Super 8 film reels have been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center, which has the proper facilities for storing and screening them. Researchers should contact the Study Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the films’ physical condition. (Box 30, Folder V.91)
  - "Homage to Victor," students working outdoors; mural, Summer 1968, 1974; From a slide carousel: color slides (Box 30, Folder V.92)
  - Southampton College art education workshop, Summer 1968; Printed flyer (Box 30, Folder V.93)
  - Teachers' workshops: students at work, finished works, 1968, 1969; Color slides (Box 30, Folder V.94)
  - Students at work indoors and outdoors, 1968-1970; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 30, Folder V.95)
  - Christmas message, May summary to the Kearsarge Art Group, 1969; Photocopied typescript (Box 30, Folder V.96)
  - Paintings by students in various classes, 1969, 1970; Color slides (Box 30, Folder V.97)
  - Carolyn self-portrait; Barbara's painting; presentation of glass bowl to Mabel D'Amico, 1969, 1970; Color slides (Box 30, Folder V.98)
  - Southampton College art education workshops, fine arts classes, 1969-1974; Administrative correspondence, student recommendations, course descriptions; includes TLS President Harry A. Marmion-D'Amico (11/22/1974) terminating the summer classes (Box 30, Folder V.99)
  - Course offerings, newsletters, posters, 1969-2007, undated; Includes D'Amico's 1969 Christmas letter to The Kearsarge Group, postcards of the Art Barge (Box 30, Folder V.100)
  - Napeague Criticism Group (1 of 2), 1970s; Includes notices from D'Amico of meetings to discuss art teaching and works in progress (Box 31, Folder V.101)
  - Napeague Criticism Group (2 of 2), 1970s; Includes D'Amico motivations, plans for painting classes. From sessions held in the off season at New York City artists' studios and at Ethical Culture School (Box 31, Folder V.102)
  - Adult students at work, [1970s]; B/w prints (Box 31, Folder V.103)
  - Class evaluations, Summer 1970; From various summer classes (Box 31, Folder V.104)
  - Southampton College Summer Art Program, 1970; Photographs of finished works: color slides (Box 31, Folder V.105)
  - Statements, correspondence with MoMA, 1970, 1975; re: Art Barge expenses (Box 31, Folder V.106)
  - Various correspondence and notes, 1970-1975, undated (Box 31, Folder V.107)
  - Correspondence with New York University re: classes, 1970-1977; Includes photocopied TLS Jerome Hausman, Professor of Art Education-Wilder Green (1/6/1970) proposing establishment of professional relationship between New York University and MoMA (Box 31, Folder V.108)
  - Summer art programs, 1970-1978; Scholarship programs for teachers: includes notices, grant-related correspondence, proposals (Box 31, Folder V.109)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1970-1979; Documentation supporting grant application (Box 31, Folder V.110)
  - Correspondence; MoMA order for building work surfaces, 1971 (Box 31, Folder V.111)
  - Forms and brochures, 1971-1979; Promotional materials and forms for classes, events, donations (Box 31, Folder V.112)
  - Exteriors, landscape at Lazy Point, 1971-1981; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 31, Folder V.113)
  - Kearsarge group: meeting notes, membership lists, 1971, 1973 (Box 31, Folder V.114)
  - Napeague Art Institute (1 of 6), 1972-1982, undated; Mailing lists (Box 31, Folder V.115)
  - Napeague Art Institute (2 of 6), 1972, 1978, 1982, undated; Clippings, writings (Box 31, Folder V.116)
  - Napeague Art Institute (3 of 6), Summer 1982; Class register: pages removed from metal-post binder (Box 31, Folder V.117)
  - Napeague Art Institute (4 of 6), Undated; Barge inventory (Box 31, Folder V.118)
  - Napeague Art Institute (5 of 6), Undated; Lists of materials and slides (Box 31, Folder V.119)
  - Napeague Art institute (6 of 6), Undated; List of East Hampton guest houses, hotels, restaurants (Box 31, Folder V.120)
  - Exhibition of student work, 1972; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 31, Folder V.121)
  - Costume party, 1972; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 31, Folder V.122)
  - Southampton College Summer Art Program, 1973-1974; Correspondence, catalogue, agreement with D'Amico (6/21/1974) re: for-credit classes held at The Art Barge (Box 31, Folder V.123)
  - Newspaper notices, 1973, 1975; Proof; letter to D'Amico accompanying notice of special New York Times Education supplement (Box 31, Folder V.124)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1973-1985; Paid notices, feature articles on D'Amico, the Art Barge, summer classes, mostly from eastern Long Island papers (Box 31, Folder V.125)
  - Correspondence with MoMA, May, August 1974; Memos re: financial arrangements between MoMA and the Napeague Institute of Art (Box 31, Folder V.126)
  - Summer art programs, 1974, 1978; Program, photographs, clipping (Box 31, Folder V.127)
  - Publicity and advertising, 1975; Photocopied information on the Napeague Institute of Art used for promotion; brochures; clippings (Box 32, Folder V.128)
  - BOCES/SCOPE, 1975; Correspondence and receipts re: funding for teacher education program (Box 32, Folder V.129)
  - New York State Council on the Arts, 1975-1976; Application for funding, summer 1976. Includes photocopied application, brochures, poster from the Napeague Art Institute (Box 32, Folder V.130)
  - Senior citizens arts and crafts classes, 1976, 1977; Attendance list, letters of thanks (Box 32, Folder V.131)
  - Senior citizens arts and crafts classes, 1976, 1977; Photographs of student work; students at work on beach and in studio: color transparencies, b/w prints (Box 32, Folder V.132)
  - Workshops for senior citizens (1 of 4), 1976; Clippings, letter of thanks, envelope (Box 32, Folder V.133)
  - Workshops for senior citizens (2 of 4), 1976-1978; Includes, correspondence, applications, recommended reading list, announcement (Box 32, Folder V.134)
  - Workshops for senior citizens (3 of 4), 1976, 1977; Photographs, letters of thanks from participants (Box 32, Folder V.135)